Uthaipon "Tao" Tantipongpipat

Machine Learning Engineer / Al Researcher

Orlando, FL, US uthaipon@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/uthaipon/

SUMMARY

Machine learning researcher at Twitter. Has driven successful fairness in Al/HCl projects (3+ billions press click-read) and led company-wide engineers in applying research based on company data. Track record (10+) of top-tier computer science (ML/Al/Statistics) publications. A PhD from Georgia Tech focused on ML theory, optimization, with 1st place award from the US government on differential privacy.

EXPERIENCE

Twitter, remote US - Machine Learning Researcher

Jun 2020 - PRESENT

- Led Twitter's image cropping algorithmic bias audit resulting in a published academic paper and \$1.5M press ad equivalency and 3B readership from 500 news articles in 49 countries. Led to another follow-up work by team members resulted in additional \$1.4M, 2.7B reads, and 800 articles from 47 additional countries, and resulted in the production change to remove the algorithm
- Proposed a 13-18% precision-recall video classification model improvement with no additional cost to partnering team to fix offensive misclassifications on Tweet topic annotations, and discovered correlation bias with demographics despite a lack of private individual data
- Established a data-driven guideline for company-wide engineers to adopt a inequality metric in A/B statistical testing, as well as winning business approval with company leadership that finally led to shipping the metric
- Provided statistical analysis to customer teams to evaluate and quantify bias in ML models;
 redesigned common ML statistical significance tests required for bias measurement
- Mentored a junior researcher
- Published two papers in social computing conference and one in data science journal

Microsoft, Redmond WA - Research Intern

May 2019 - July 2019

- Implemented privacy guarantee on large-scale natural language processing models (RNNs and LSTMs) to protect against personal deidentification due to model usage
- Developed novel correlation clustering algorithm with corresponding privacy analysis
- Researched private submodular optimization and surveyed literature for private stochastic gradient descent for improving training deep learning models
- Published one paper in the machine learning conference NeurlPS

EDUCATION

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta GA

PhD in Algorithms, Combinatorics, and Optimization (ACO)

Aug 2016 - May 2020

Minor in Computational Learning Theory. GPA 4.00/4.00

Thesis: Fair and Diverse Data Representation in Machine Learning

University of Richmond, Richmond VA

BS in Mathematics, Honors with Thesis (Algebraic Combinatorics)

Aug 2012 - May 2016

Minor in Computer Science. GPA 3.97/4.00

University of Oxford, Oxford UK

Study Abroad Program in Mathematics and Computer Science Oct 2014 - Jun 2015

AWARDS

Academic:

•	Impact Recognition Award, CSCW (the social computing conference)	2021
•	ACO Outstanding Student Award (best PhD student in the year at the graduation)	2020
•	Best Reviewers of NeurIPS (top-tier machine learning conference)	2019
•	Full-merit 4-year scholarship for tuition and living expense, University of Richmond 2012	- 2016

Competitions:

- 1st Prize Award and People's Choice Award (\$20,000 total), The Unlinkable Data Challenge,
 National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), US Department of Commerce
- Finalist, Tech Challenge programming competition, Illinois Technology Association, IL 2016
- 2nd Place, ICPC Mid-Atlantic USA Regional Contest, Christopher Newport University
 2015
- Honorable Mention (top 2.5%), William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition 2015
- Bronze Medal and Honorable Mention, Asia-Pacific Mathematics Olympiad (APMO) 2010, 2011
- Gold and Bronze Medals, IWYMIC International Mathematics Competition 2008, 2009

PUBLICATIONS

I have 11 peer-reviewed published papers, mainly in top-tier CS venues (such as NeurIPS, COLT, SODA). Topics include machine learning, differential privacy, fairness, algorithms/theory, statistics, and HC/Social Computing. My website www.uthaipon.com or Google Scholar has full details.

SKILLS

Technical: Python, Java, C++, SQL (BigQuery), Pytorch, pandas, numpy, scipy, Git, CVXOPT,

MATLAB, Mathematica, LaTeX, MS Office

Languages: Thai (native); English (full proficiency)